牛逼字幕,二雷制作
(LEO修改版20131123)
你为什么总是这样？
Why must you be this way?
为什么我们总有分歧？ 这是个问题。
Why is there always a problem? It's a good question.
你想回家吗？ 你想掉头回家吗？
Do you want to go home? Do you want to turn around?
- 是! - 那可是喜玛拉雅!
- Yes! - It's the Himalayas!
喜玛拉雅山，我和你谈论多久了？
How long have I been talking about the Himalayas?
- 多久？ - 很久了。
- How long? - Far too long.
Horst,我们什么时候到, 你能快一点吗?
Horst, when we get there, can you give me a hand, please?
- 当然。 - Ingrid，安静一会！
- Yes, of course. - Ingrid, stop it.
我们一定要把这件事情做好。
Let's try to make the best of this.
那个想见我们的白痴在哪？
Where's thls idiot who's supposed to meet us?
劳驾!
Move!
Harrer 先生。
Mr. Harrer.
你的票在我这。
I have your tickets.
-我迟到了，带我去车厢吧。 - 哦，你误会了。
- I'm late. Take me to my train. - No, you don't understand.
我是 Peter Aufschnaiter。 我是探险队的队长。
I am Peter Aufschnaiter. I am leading the expedition.
- 你好！ - 我们英雄在这里！
- How do you do? - Here's our celebrity!
Harrer 先生?
Mr. Harrer?
Harrer 先生， 我以 Reichssportsfuhrer（德语：国家体委主任）的名义……
May I say, Mr. Harrer, on behalf of the Reichssportsfuhrer...
我们为探险队有这样的德国英雄而感到自豪！
we are honored to have such a great German hero on the team.
谢谢， 但是我是奥地利人。
Thank you, but I'm Austrian.
我知道。 但是我确信—— 作为国家社会党的杰出代表
Yes. but I'm sure that . as a distinguished member...
当你将国旗插上南迦帕尔巴特峰（Nanga Parbat）时，
of the National Soclalist Party, you would be proud to plant...
你会感到自豪！
our country's flag on the summit of Nanga Parbat when you reach it.
Hans Lobenhoffer（人名）
Hans Lobenhoffer.
Lutz Chicken（人名）
Lutz Chicken.
和你漂亮的妻子合一张影。
And a picture with your lovely wife.
还有那位先生——嗯——
And Mr.--
Horst lmmendorf。好朋友。 没必要拍照了。
Horst lmmendorf. Family frlend. No plcture necessary.
孩子什么时候出生？ Harrer夫人？
When is the little one due. . Mrs. Harrer?
大概是我丈夫到达营地的时候。
About the time my husband reaches the base camp.
谢谢。
Thank you.
你为什么不告诉那整个腐朽的国家我们的麻烦？
Why don't you tell the entire stinking country our troubles?
我要上车了。 你还有什么话想说？
I'm getting on that train. Do you have anything you want to say?
就这样吧。
Fine.
走吧！
Go. Leave.
四个月以后见。
I'll see you in four months.
-好好照顾她， Horst。 -没问题， Heinrich 。 。
- Take good care of her, Horst. - I will. Heinrich . .
我们行程5000英里，
We will travel 5,000 miles.
到达印度， 然后动身去喜玛拉雅，
When we reach lndia, we will head for the Hlmalayas...
接着向世界第九高峰出发， 南迦帕尔巴特峰（Nanga Parbat）
and the ninth highest peak on Earth, Nanga Parbat.
德国称作“Unserberg-- 我们的山峰。”
Germany calls it "Unserberg-- Our Mountain. "
在我们之前，四支德国探险队尝试过
Before us, four German expeditions attempted it.
都失败了。
All failed.
11名登山队员在风暴和雪崩中丧身。
Eleven climbers were killed in storms and avalanches.
直到现在征服南迦帕尔巴特峰（Nanga Parbat） 还是这个国家的阴影--
By now, the conquest of Nanga Parbat is a national obsession--
关系到德国的自尊
a matter of German pride.
1939年7月29日
July 29, 1939.
我们在海拔22000英尺的地方扎营。
We have already made Camp Four at 22.000 feet. .
头顶是 Reklak 冰河和难以攀登的冰崩（icefall）。
Overhead is the Reklak Glacier and a difficult climb up the icefall.
孩子已经一个月大了。
The baby must be at least one month old now.
我感到困惑，心烦意乱。
I have been so confused and dlstracted.
不能象往常一样自信地攀登
I can 't climb with my usual confldence.
你没事吧？
Are you all right?
Shit!
- 你没事吧？ - 要下来帮你吗？
- Are you al I right? - Shall we come down?
只是掉了个鞋钉。
Lost a crampon !
继续前进！
Go ahead!
天气很糟， 大家应该用绳子绑在一起。
The weather's getting bad. We should rope up.
- 你受伤了吗？ - 只是擦伤， 我要走到前面去。
- Did you hurt yourself back there? - Just a scratch. I'll lead.
岩石！
Rocks!
向下看！
Look out below!
抓住我！
Hold me!
你抓住我了吗?
Have you got me?
抓住我！
Hold me!
你应该告诉我伤口的情况，
You should have told me how bad that wound was.
我就可以查看一下， 然后帮你缝合伤口。
I should take a look at lt. I could sew it up.
这不关你的事！
It's not your problem.
事实上， 这就是我的事。
Actually, it is my problem.
- 他关系到我的生命。 -什么？
- It's my life. - What?
当你隐瞒你受重伤的事实时， 我的生命就置于危险之中
When you conceal a serious injury and put my life at risk...
所以那是我的事情。
I consider th at my problem.
不， 是你把自己的生命置于危险之中， 而我救了你！ 所以你给我闭嘴！
No, you put your life at rlsk. I saved it, so shut up !
Please, it is not your place--
闭嘴！
Shut up !
如果下一次你还隐瞒伤情 那么 Heinrich。。。
The next time you lle about an lnjury, Heinrich...
你将被开除。
you're off the team.
走着瞧。
Try it.
8月4号， 五号营地。 强烈的风暴过去了
August 4th, Camp Five. Some fierce storms have passed.
我的队友担心雪崩随时会发生
My teammates are nervous about the avalanches...
于是我们不得不驻留几天。
so we 've been holed up for days.
Aufschnalter 应该将营地扎在低谷，而不是在高处
Aufschnalter should take advantage of this lowland weather to make high camp.
但是他不同意我的意见。 白痴！
But he disagrees with me. Fool.
好像其他的队友都不介意在原地坐等
It seems the others don 't mind sitting here waiting...
除了祈祷无事可做。
hoping, doing nothing.
太多的自问绝对不是一件好事
So much time to question one 's self is not good.
我开始认为这次探险是一个错误
I am beginnlng to think this whole expedition was a mistake.
快跑！ 雪崩！出来！
Run ! Avalanche! Get out!
什么都不要带！
Leave everything!
把它放下！
Put that down !
我们现在要下山！
We are going down now!
如果他们害怕风暴，那就送他们去2号营地
If they're frightened of a storm, send them down to Camp Two.
我可以一个人登顶！ Always give the best man his shot!
I could summit on my own ! Always give the best man his shot!
他想告诉我们他是最强的
He's trying to tell us he's the best man.
给我两个夏尔巴人（Sherpa登山能力超强的一个西藏种族） 今晚我就可以建立6号营地
Give me two Sherpas. I can make Camp Six by tonight...
明天我就登顶！
and my final attack tomorrow!
-我们必须整队下山！ - 那个顶峰是我的！
- We are going down now as a team! - I've earned that peak!
- 我渴望顶峰！ - 全队！ 这是命令！
- I want th at peak! - As a team! That's an order!
这是命令！ 命令！
That is an order! An order!
跟着我！
Follow me!
达赖喇嘛的神像。会保护我们
Dalai Lama photo. Good protection.
带着它， Si Hib， 它会保护你
Take it. Si Hib. . It will protect you.
不，对我来说这毫无意义
No, that means nothing to me.
达赖喇嘛。达赖喇嘛的神像
Dalai Lama. Dalai Lama photo.
Si Hib，带着它
Si Hib, take it.
它会保护你
Good protection for you.
下午好， Herr Harrer
Good afternoon, Herr Harrer.
嘿， 希望德国人从波兰撤退
Well, let's hope that Germany retreats from Poland...
象你们下山一样快
as quickly as you did from your mountain.
你现在应该进监狱呆会了
It might save you some prison time.
什么？你是谁？
What is this? Who are you?
- 我很抱歉，但是你被逮捕了 - 什么罪名？登顶失败？
- I'm sorry, but you're under arrest. - What charge? Failure to summit?
恐怕不是
I'm afraid not.
你知道……不列颠王国已经向德国宣战
You see, war has been declared between Hls Majesty's Government and Germany.
所有大英帝国领土上的敌人 现在都是战俘了
So all enemy aliens on British Empire soil are now prisoners of war.
-站住，否则开枪了！ - 举起手来！
- Stop, or I'll shoot! - Hands up!
不，你们什么都不知道！ 我是奥地利人！ 我是登山队员！
No, you don't understand! I'm Austrian ! I'm a cllmber!
我和你们的狗屁战争毫无关系
I have nothing to do with your silly war!
让我自己走！ 这是对我的侮辱！
I can walk myself. This is an insult!
你们以为可以逮捕我， 但是你们没有权利这样做！
You think you have the last word, but you don't!
猪！ 都是猪！
Pigs! All of you, pigs!
1939年10月15日
October 15, 1939.
抵达战俘营。我对自己说
Reaching prison camp, I make a promise to myself.
明年夏至之前我会回到 lngrid 身边
I will be lying beside lngrid before the summer solstice of the new year.
喜马拉雅山脉就在我们前方
The Hlmalayas are right in front of us.
逃跑并不困难，并且可以隐没在群山之中
It will be easy to escape and get lost in them.
第四次逃跑的尝试，并没有使我离成功跟近
My fourth escape attempt brings me no closer to my goal.
这次你跑了多远？
How far did you get this time?
唯一的成果是——在战俘营中我似乎成了一个名人
All I have achieved is a certaln dubious celebrity among the prisoners.
要是手中的笔能够写出心里所想的该多好
If only my hand could express what is ln my heart.
我听说卫兵会帮你寄信
I hear the guards are mailing letters for you.
是的
Yes.
可以帮我寄这个吗？
Would you mail these?
谢谢
Thank you.
Hey, Heinrich, 你看过这本书吗？
Hey, Heinrich, have you read this book?
是关于你的
It was checked out to you.
- 我们得和你谈谈 - 关于什么？
- We need to talk to you. - What about?
关于这些。
About this.
难以置信。 你们打算什么时候行动？
Impressive. When do you plan to leave?
雨季结束后。 你呢？
After monsoon season. And you?
我想你们选择了我穿越西藏的路线
I see you've chosen my route through Tibet.
几乎没有外国人在那条路上生还。 祝你们好运。
The few foreigners who have tried never came back. So, good luck.
-你愿意和我们一起行动吗？ - 为什么？
- Would you like to come with us? - Why?
毕竟，你是这里的越狱专家
After all, you are the authority on jailbreak around here.
- 你的经验将使我们受益
- We could benefit from your experience. - Please.
停止这个尴尬的游戏吧
Stop this embarrassing charade.
每次你逃跑之后， 巡逻的卫兵都会是原来的两三倍
Every time you escape, the patrols are doubled and tripled.
对于我们中的其他人而言，这使生活变得非常困难
It is making life very difficult for the rest of us.
我更喜欢一个人旅行， 不过还是谢谢你的忠告。
I prefer to travel on my own, but thanks for thinking of me.
邮递员来过了。
The mailman has come.
亲爱的Heinrlch:
Dear Heinrlch:
请在随信附上的离婚协议上签字，并寄给我的律师
Please sign the enclosed dlvorce papers and send them to my lawyer.
Horst和我打算在我们的离婚手续办妥之后立刻结婚
Horst and I intend to be married as soon as the divorce is flnalized.
至于你的来信我收到了
As for your letter, yes.
你的儿子 Rolf Harrer 在你登山的时候出生的
Your son, Rolf Harrer, was born while you were climbing the mountain.
现在两岁了，喊 Horst 爸爸
He is now two years old and calls Horst "papa. "
当他足够大的时候 我会告诉他
When he is old enough, I will tell him...
他的生父在喜马拉雅山失踪了。
his real father was lost in the Himalayas.
由于你从来都没想过要这个孩子
It seems the kindest thing to say consldering...
我想这是最好的方式告诉孩子关于他父亲的故事
you never wanted the child anyway.
不必说了，我不打算
Needless to say, I have no intention...
象你说的那样去解决我们自己的分歧了
of "resolving our differences " as you suggested.
他们在你离开奥地利的时候都已经解决了
They were resolved the moment you left Austria.
我很难过你在印度被监禁
I'm sorry you have been imprisoned ln lndia...
并且希望这场可恶的战争 象所有人希望的那样早日结束
and hope this dreadful war will soon be over for everyone's sake.
Ingrid。
Ingrid.
我和你们一起走
I'm coming with you.
这是你们的计划？
This is your plan?
以我的拙见，这很荒谬
In my humble opinion, this is ridiculous.
既然这样， 我们不会征求你的意见
Then since you are so humble, we won't ask your opinion.
打开地图，转过身去
Open the charts. Turn around.
背对大门 打开地图！
Keep your back to the gate. Open the charts!
一直说话， 按我的信号行动
Keep talking. Wait for my signal.
警报解除。 Okay。
We are clear. Okay.
开门!
Open the gates!
看这个。 开门!
See to this. Open the gates!
我一个人逃。
I'm going off on my own.
祝你们好运
So, good luck.
第一次越狱 1939年11月18日
First escape from prlson camp, November 18, 1939.
Rolf Harrer--三个半月大
Rolf Harrer-- three and a half months old.
1941年7月6日30岁生日
My 30th birthday, July 6, 1941.
Rolf Harrer-- 正好一岁, 11个月零26天
Rolf Harrer-- exactly one year, 11 months and 26 days.
最后一次从Dehra Dun越狱 Rolf Harrer--
Last escape from Dehra Dun. Rolf Harrer--
吃两片药睡一觉就好了 天亮的时候我会给你送钱来的。
Take two and sleep it off. I'll send you a bill in the morning.
你在这里干什么？
What are you doing here?
我很想念你 所以我就来拜访你
I missed you so much. I thought I'd pay you a visit.
其他的人呢？
What about the others?
出了 Nelang 意大利人就被抓住了。
The ltalians were caught outside Nelang.
Lutz 和 Hans 病了 不得不回去。
Lutz and Hans got sick and had to turn back.
- 我很难过听到这些。 - 我相信你说的是真的。
- Sorry to hear that. - I'm sure you're heartbroken.
我可以在这里扎营过夜吗？
May I impose upon your generous nature and camp here tonight?
荣幸之至
Be my guest.
谢谢
Thank you. It is very gracious of you.
你在这里还干些什么？
- Good. - What else do you have in there?
组织一个管弦乐团？
A ten-piece orchestra?
我听说日本人撤退了
By the way, I heard the Japanese have retreated...
已经在退往上海的路上了
all the way back to Shanghai so even if you make it to the Chinese border...
所以即使现在你在中国的边境上， 你也很难追上他们了
you may have dlfficulty catchlng up with them.
我不关心这些，哪怕他们向东京撤退
I don 't care if they're repelled all the way back to Tokyo.
如果想回奥地利，你就该关心
You should if you want to get back to Austria.
- 但是我不想。 - 什么？
- But I don't. - Don't what?
- 回家。 - 为什么不？
- Plan to go back. - Why not?
没有理由。
No particular reason.
你回去的时候， 告诉我妻子
When you get there, tell my wife...
四年的婚姻和两年的监狱生活没什么区别
that two years in prison camp is roughly equivalent to four years of marriage.
我很高兴能同时逃出两座围城
And I'm glad to be free of them both.
我也不会回去，即使该死的战争结束了
I'm not golng back either, not until this shameful war is over.
- 那你准备去哪？ - 西藏
- And where are you headed? - Tibet.
然后去中国， 看能不能在那里找到工作
Then on to China. . see if I can find some work there.
你呢？
And you ?
按照我的计算，这里离中国的边境有2058公里
By my calculations, the Chinese border is 2,058 kilometers away.
离西藏68公里
Tibet is 68.
你不可能带那么多东西走那么远
It's a long way to travel with such a heavy load.
不多，全是食品
No, just full of food.
- 听起来不错 - 嗯
- Precisely. - Mine.
这太糟了。
That's too bad.
那些山脉反复无常（经常有雪崩）。 还有冰河要穿越
Those mountains are treacherous. There are glaciers to be crossed.
如果你和我绑在一起 我能保证你活着
If you had roped up to me, I could have kept you alive.
考虑到最后一次绑在一起登山时你的表现
Considering your performance the last time we roped up...
没有你我更安全
I think I'm safer without you.
那好！
Of course.
我想你算错了， 关于这里离西藏边界有多远
But I think you are wrong about that Tibetan border calculatlon.
按照我的计算是65公里
By my measurements, it is 65 kilometers.
赌一公斤食品？
Care to wager a kilo of food on that?
可你只有一些烂饼干
All you've got is some stale crackers.
但是我是对的。 我会赢。
But I'm right. I'll win.
西藏，世界屋脊
Tibet, the roof of the world.
感觉就像登上了一座中世纪的城堡
It feels as though we have ascended a medieval stone fortress...
高耸在亚洲中心
towering above the center of Asla.
这是地球上最高的地区
This ls the highest country on Earth.
也是最孤独的
And the most isolated.
到了。
There it is.
西藏
Tibet.
- 正好68公里 - 恭喜
- Exactly 68 kilometers. - Congratulations.
不幸的是你已经把你赢的都吃光了
Unfortunately, you've eaten all your winnings.
yes
Yes.
只管笑，然后说yes 这样最好
Just smile and say yes. It's better that way.
这是你在监狱里学到的？令人吃惊
It's amazing what you learn in prison, isn't it?
西藏。
Tibet.
- 外国人不能入藏 - oh，please!
- No foreigners allowed in Tlbet. - Oh, please!
外国人不能入藏!
No foreigner!
Oh, please!
Yes。 Thank you。 Of course。
Yes. Thank you. Of course.
我们不需要翻译
No translation needed.
有些人看见我们很高兴
Some people are glad to see us.
别被它迷惑了。。。
Don't let it get to your head.
。。。藏族人拍手代表驱赶邪恶的力量
When the Tibetans clap hands, it means they are driving out evil forces.
给我们一些吃的
We need to find food.
这是个预言。。。
It is the prophecy. It says here...
十三世达赖喇嘛在他的遗嘱中说。。。
in the final testament of great thirteenth Dalai Lama.
西藏的宗教和政府。。。
"It may happen that, in Tibet, religions and government...
将来会受到异族的威胁。
will be attacked by outside forces.
如果我们不能保护西藏。。。
Unless we can guard our own country...
。。。喇嘛和寺庙将有灭顶之灾;
monks and their monasteries will be destroyed.
我们的土地和财产将被剥夺;
The lands and property of government officials will be seized.
达赖喇嘛和他所有的信徒。。。
The Dalai Lama an d all the revered holders of the faith...
。。。都将消失,隐匿。
will disappear and become nameless."
现在你知道我们为什么不欢迎外国人了?
Now you understand why we are not welcome to forelgners here?
是的，但是你们应该知道 我们并不是来威胁、伤害你们的
Yes, but you must understand we're not here to threaten or harm.
我们只想要点食物，然后上路……
We just need food, and then we'll be on our--
Garpon（探子）来了
His Excellency, the Garpon.
尊敬的阁下, 很高兴见到你们
Your Eminence, we're happy to see you.
我们想道歉
We wanted to apologize.
道歉。
Apologize.
还想给你们这个特殊的礼物
And give you this really special gift.
我们的心意
Please, from us.
达赖喇嘛万岁
Long live the Dalai Lama, Hi s Holiness.
谢谢你们的圣像， 回印度去吧
Thank you for the picture. Go back to lndla!
进入西藏西部边境两天之后 我们被体面地赶了出来
Two days into Tibet 's western frontier and we are graciously klcked out.
向导押送我们。。。
Our guides have strict orders to escort us...
直到我们进入印度边境40公里
to the lndian border some 40 kllometers away...
如果我们企图逃跑他们就会开枪
and to shoot us if we attempt escape.
我想这表示打招呼
Must mean hello.
只要他们不来亲我。
As long as they don't try to kiss me.
－我们必须补充给养。 －我破产了。
We have to stock up. I'm broke.
别看我。
Don't look at me.
我们必须吃点东西了,Peter。 知道现在几点了吗?
We have to eat. Peter. . Know what time it is?
没得商量。
It is not negotiable.
那是我登上Blanc山时我爸爸给我的礼物
My father gave it to me when I climbed Mount BI anc.
每个人都登过Blanc山。
Everyone's climbed Mount Blanc.
如果我有一块这样的手表, 现在我会把它卖了的。
If I had a watch like this, I would trade it.
-这件甲克从哪来的? - 西藏北边。
- Where did you get this jacket? - North Tibet.
从中国来的共产主义战士非常好。
Communlsm soldier come from Chin a. Very nice.
他们分食物、发钱。 共产主战士。
They give food, money. Very nice. Communism soldier.
你喜欢军装，是吗？
You like military uniforms, yes?
我送你一双德国军用鞋子好吗？
I have German army boots. For you. Yes?
等一会。
Wait.
给我这个, 防滑用的
Give me these, for the guards.
Look!
就是这样。 你喜欢吗?
Like this. You like?
非常好。 很实用的
Very good. They're tough.
哥们, 你想知道德国士兵怎么走路吗？
My friend, shall I show you how German soldiers march?
你脸上必须是这种表情。
You must make this face.
走! 对了。
Come! Yes.
停!
Stop!
非常好。你还需要练习
Excellent. Yes. You, with practice.
现在, 我向你演示德国士兵怎是么跑的。
Now, I will show you how German soldiers run.
先这样站好。
Stand like this.
看什么呢?
Guess what?
没人了。
All clear.
知道现在几点了?
Know what time it is?
你以为和你一起走我很快乐。。。
You think I'm so happy to be traveling with you...
而且我要为此买单?
I should foot the bill?
你好强呀，你就什么也不用贡献？
You are such a blg man you don't need to contribute?
怎么了?
You have a problem?
告诉我。。。
Remind me...
在刚才那个集市你怎么说的。
what you said at the bazaar back there.
"如果我有一块这样的手表，现在我会把它卖了。"
"If I had a watch like that, I would trade it."
你确实没有一块。
You do not have one.
骗子! 你有三块!
You cheap, lying bastard! You have three!
这是从意大利战俘拿来的垃圾。
This is junk from some ltalian prisoners.
不要和我解释!
I don't give a shit!
你听说过原则吗?
Haven't you ever heard of a principle?
什么原则?
What principle?
你想要一块手表? 捡一块走。。。。
You want a watch? Go ahead. Pick one.
- 。。。遵守你原则去吧。 - 看看你自己 !
- And keep your principles. - Look at you !
自私、乳臭未干、自以为是
Caught being a selfish brat and you're gloating !
你像个女人。 你想要什么?
You're acting like an old woman. What do you want?
试着道歉。
Try apologizing.
试着去反省
Try feeling a little remorse.
如果这些你都做不到, 那就试着去把你脸上的傻笑擦掉！
And if all else fail s, try wiping that smirk off your face!
拿着你的手表，然后给我闭嘴。
Take your stinking watch and shut up!
我不再想听到烦人的说教
I don't need another boring sermon from some frustrated glorified tour guide.
毫无疑问你永远是孤独的。
No wonder you are always alone.
没有人可以忍受可怜的你
No one can stand your miserable company.
拿着吧。
Please, take them.
是我错了把它们藏起来。
It was wrong of me to hide them.
- 拿着。 - 不。
- Keep this. - No.
我也不该得到它。 走吧。
I didn't deserve It either. Go ahead.
他现在应该三岁半了。
He'll be three and a half years old now.
不久她就会告诉他， 我在喜马拉雅山失踪了
Pretty soon, she'll tell him I was lost in the Himalayas.
这真不错。
Which is fine.
为什么?
Why?
一个死去的爸爸总比不负责的爸爸好
Better a dead father than a lousy father.
给他写封信。
Write him a letter.
让他知道你还活着。
Let him know you're still alive.
纽约。
New York.
威尼斯。
Venice.
- 巴黎。 - Your Holiness, 你在哪里?
- Paris. - Your Holiness, where are you?
你该上课了。
It ls time for your lesson.
Your Holiness,你在哪里? 你该上课了。
Your Holiness, where are you? It is time for your lesson.
亲爱的 Rolf Harrer:
Dear Rolf Harrer:
我是一个你不认识的人。。。
I'm a person you don 't know...
一个你从未遇见过的人。
a man you 've never met.
但你却萦绕我的脑海。。。
But you are someone who occupies my mind...
。。。占据我的心灵。。。
and my heart...
尽管我们相隔万里。
in this dlstant land where I have gone.
如果你可以想象地球上一个被悄悄隐藏在。。。
If you can imagine a hidden place tucked safely away from the world...
。。。高耸的城墙和雪山之下;
concealed by walls of high, snowcapped mountains--
充满着梦幻般美景的地方。
a place rich with all the strange beauty of your nighttime dreams--
那就是现在我脚下的这片土地。
then you know where I am.
－西藏。。。
In the country where I am traveling, Tibet...
那里的人们相信, 如果不远万里前去朝圣。。。
people believe if they walk long distances to holy places...
。。。所犯的罪孽将得到宽恕。
It purifles the bad deeds they've committed.
而且他们相信朝圣的路途越艰险。。。
They believe the more difficult the journey...
心灵的净化就越彻底。
the greater the depth of purification.
我从一个遥远的地方前往另一个遥远的圣地。。。
I've been walking from one faraway place to the next for many years--
。。。路途象生命一样漫长。
as long as you have lived.
我看见高原上四季变迁,
I have seen seasons change across the high plateaus.
看见冬天藏野驴向南迁徙。。。
I have seen wild kiangs migrate south in winter...
。。。当春天的来临时候他们悄悄又回来。
and sweep back across the fields when spring appears.
在这里只要时间存在。。。
In this place, where time stands still...
。。。一切似乎都在变化,
it seems that everything is moving...
包括我自己。
including me.
我不知道自己要去哪里。。。
I can 't say I know where I'm going...
也不知道罪孽是否会被宽恕。
nor whether my bad deeds can be purified.
我后悔很多过去的事情,
There are so many things I have done which I regret.
但是当我达到那个遥远的终点时, 我希望你能明白。。。
But when I come to a full stop, I hope you will understand...
。。。我们之间的距离并不象看起来那么遥远。
that the distance between us is not as great as it seems.
深爱你的爸爸
Wlth deep affection...
Heinrlch Harrer。
your father, Heinrlch Harrer.
起来。
Get up.
上帝!
My God!
我把这个给你。
I'll give you these.
黄头发!
Yellow head!
- No! Wait! 我们一无所有! - 把钱交出来!
- No! Wait! We have nothing! - Give me money!
我们没有钱!
We have no money!
手表也行!
Give me watch !
-把衣服给我! - 我们什么也没有 !
- Give me clothes! - We have nothing for you !
等一会!
Wait!
你们去哪里?
Where are you headed?
我有通行证。
I have permit.
拉萨。 我有通行证。
Lhasa. I have permit.
对于西藏的精神领袖来说窥看他的人民是不体面的。
It is unseemly for the spiritual leader of Tibet to spy on people.
就在一个月前, 我们几乎死在强盗手里。
Only a month ago, we were certain of death at the hands of bandits.
而今天我们已经来到了禁城－拉萨的大门。
And today, we have reached the gates of the forbidden city of Lhasa.
它象麦加一样难以企及并且充满诱惑。。。
It is as difficult a goal as Mecca...
因为它的大门从不向任何外国人开放。
and preclsely as attractive because it ls closed to all foreigners.
即使在如此糟糕的情况之下。。。
Even in our miserable condition...
。。。我们依然能感到圣城拉萨的诱惑
we feel the lure of Tlbet 's holiest city...
那里是达赖喇嘛的家。
home of the Dalai Lama.
只有很少的外国人得以洞察她的神秘。
Only a few foreigners had penetrated its mysteries.
哦, 上帝!
Oh, my God!
-结束了? -没有。
- Is It over? - No. it is not over. .
如果你们愿意的话可以留下来吃午饭。
You are invited to stay for lunch, if you like.
我们非常愿意。
We'd like that very much.
我是 Tsarong。 欢迎来我家。
I am Tsarong. Welcome to my home.
我叫 Peter。
I am Peter.
Lord Chamberlain(官名,宫务大臣), 我可以见。。。
Lord Chamberlain, may I request...
the Regent(摄政者) 和 the Minister of the cabinet(内阁大臣)吗?
an audlence with the regent and ministers of the cabinet?
关于两个来到西藏的外国人。
It's about two foreigners who came to Lhasa.
尊敬的 Rinpoche。。。
With respect, Rinpoche...
如果你的意图是阻止中国人以联盟国的名义征兵。。。
If your intention is to stop the Chinese from recruiting political allies...
。。。然后要求他们停止向僧侣行贿
then demanding that they stop trying to bribe monks...
这不是最有效的策略。
is not the most effective tactic.
我是在向大臣征求意见, 而不是一个小小的秘书。
I asked the opinion of the ministers, not that of a mere secretary.
当然。 原谅我的无礼。
Of course. Forgive me.
你可以离开了。
You may leave now.
把信件翻译出来。
Start translating the letter as written .
好的。
Of course.
你知道有几个人可以从这样残酷的经历中幸存?
Do you realize how many men could survive such an ordeal?
我们应该尊重他们。
We should respect them.
如果我们把他们送回印度, 他们肯定又会回到监狱。
If we return them to lndla, they'll surely go back to prison.
但是他们在这里毫无目的, Kungo Tsaron, 也无处可住。
But they have no purpose here, Kungo Tsarong. No place to live.
我已经邀请他们在我家的客房住下了。。。
I have invited them to stay at my guest quarters...
我想你也一定会允许他们留在拉萨的。
assuming you would grant them permission to remain in Lhasa, of course.
邀请他们在你家住?
Invited them to stay at your place?
为什么?
But why?
帮助困境中的人需要理由吗?
Must one have reason to help those in need?
Beast。
Beast.
她说你很臭。
I think she said you stink.
你们用不着自我介绍,
You do not need to introduce yourselves.
我知道你们是谁。
I know who you are.
我叫 Pema Lhaki。
I am Pema Lhaki.
Ngawang 想给你们一个礼物, 所以请把衣服脱了。
Ngawang wishes to make a gift to you, so please take your clothes off.
快一点, 我不会给你们一整天时间。
Let's get started. I don't have all day.
哦, Ngawang Jigme真是太客气了。
Well, this is most kind of Ngawang Jigme.
他想关心谁呢?
Who is he to be so thoughtful?
总理的秘书。。。
Secretary to the ministers of the government.
。。。想给你们一套新衣服作为礼物。
He wished to make you a gift of new clothes.
请选一下你们喜欢的式样。
Please select your preferred article of clothing.
你是裁缝?
You're a seamstress?
我是裁缝, 拉萨唯一的裁缝。。。
I am a tailor, sir, the only tailor in Lhasa...
。。。曾经去过加尔各答 能够缝制一些简单的衣服。
who has been to Calcutta and can reproduce these silly costumes.
我挑了?
So, I pick?
嗯,随便哪件都可以。
Yes, choose whichever you like.
- 这些你都会做? - 是的。
- And you can make any of these? - Yes.
- 太好了。 - 你自己做的?
- Very good. - Did you make this?
-是的。 - 很漂亮。
- Yes. - Beautiful.
- 谢谢。 - 你喜欢这个吗?
- Th ank you. - Do you like this?
只要你喜欢。
Whichever you like.
我想要这件漂亮的斜纹呢夹克,
I will have this handsome tweed jacket.
和这条软呢运动裤子。
And this pair of sporting woolen trousers, please.
- 非常好的选择。 - 谢谢。
- Good choice. - Thanks.
你呢, 先生?
And you, sir?
- 或许你可以为我挑选。 - 谢谢。
- Perhaps you could choose for me. - Thank you.
请脱掉藏袍。 我要量一下。
Please, sir, take off your chu-pa. I would like to measure.
请站直。
Stand still, please.
这边。
Thls way, please.
- 请站直。 -对不起。
- Stand still. - Sorry.
-不要动。 -对不起。
- No moving, please. - I'm sorry.
这样你就不会掉下来。 完美。
That way, you will never fall. It's perfect.
为了爬山而爬山不是有点傻吗? Heinrich。
Still, walking up mountain s is a fool's pleasure, Heinrich.
不傻, 真的。
Not so foolish, really.
看这个。
Look at this.
看看。
Go ahead.
这些是在我登上 Eiger(艾尔格)峰北坡后拍的。
That's after I climbed the Eiger North Face.
这是奥林匹克金牌。 不过没什么。
That's Olympics. Gold medal. Not important.
这就是我们在文化上的另一个巨大差异。
Then this is another great difference between our civilization and yours.
你们崇拜。。。
You admire the man...
。。。何种职业中勇于攀登顶峰的人,
who pushes his way to the top in any walk of life...
而我们崇拜放弃自我的人。
while we admire the man who abandons his ego.
藏民一般都不会以这种方式生活。
The average Tibetan wouldn't think to thrust himself forward this way.
先生。
Gentlemen.
- 对不起,我们认识吗? - 没有。
- I'm sorry. Have we met? - No, we have not.
我叫 Ngawang Jigme。
I am Ngawang Jigme.
- 哦, 想起来了。 -原谅我们。
- Yes, of course. - Forgive us.
谢谢你慷慨的礼物。
Thank you for your generous gift.
非常好。 谢谢。
It's wonderful. Thank you.
没什么。 我想我们会再见面的。
You are most welcome. I am sure we will meet again.
你或许可以向我们解释。。。
Perhaps you could help us explain...
为什么大臣(the ministers)。。。
why the min isters...
。。。要求中国政府停止。。。
demand that the Chinese government...
。。。对喇嘛的
"...cease making generous financlal contributions...
。。。慷慨经济援助。
to Tibetan monasteries."
我们的援助让你们的政府不高兴吗?
Do our gifts displease your government?
我不能代表the regent 或者 the ministers说话, 很抱歉。
I cannot speak for the regent nor the ministers, Excellence.
我只是一个小小的秘书。
I am only a mere secretary.
不会很久了, 我相信。 请坐。
Not for long, I presume. Sit down.
一个像你这样极具天赋的人应该不会满足。。。
A man of such obvious talent cannot be satisfied...
。。。仅仅翻译信件吧。
with just translating letters.
你的外交才能。。。
Your diplomatic skill...
将在这里收到丰厚的回报。
would be richly rewarded here.
忠诚的为西藏服务对我来说就足够了, 抱歉。
Serving my country faithfully is reward enough, Excellence.
我现在可以走了吗。
I ask permission to take my leave.
今天我们好像都需要一个好裁缝。
It looks like we're both in need of a good tailor today.
是的, 这有点……
Yes, there's a--
请坐一会。
Please, take a seat.
你喜欢这个? 我买给你。
Do you like these? I'll buy them for you.
谢谢你, 但是我不经常吃肉。
Thank you, but I don't eat much meat.
- 不吃肉? -他们告诉我这是西方的刀。
- Don't eat meat? - He says they are knives from West.
把它穿在脚上用来切肉。
You put them on your feet to cut meat.
这是溜冰鞋。
They are ice skates.
穿着可以。。。
You put them on your feet...
溜冰。。。
to skate...
在冰上滑行-- 就是一种冰上舞蹈。
to glide-- sort of dance on ice.
为什么？
- Yeah. - Why?
- 为什么不? - 这是另一种傻傻的娱乐。
- Why n ot? - It's another fool's pleasure.
把它买下。
Let's get them. How mu--
不，是这个?
No, for this?
十元。
Ten.
这个呢?
And for this?
你看见了吗?
Did you see?
看见了吗?
Did you see that?
-你伤着了吗? - 没有, 谢谢你。 我没事。
- Did you hurt yourself? - No, thank you. I'm okay.
我们继续。 站起来。
Here we go. Up.
- 你没事吧? 有撞着头吗? - 没有,我很开心。
- You okay? Did you bang your head? - No, I'm having fun.
- 你必须先要站住。 - 看着我!
- You must hold on. - Watch me!
- 只要看着我的眼睛就可以了。 - 对了,就这样。
- Do not look too much at the ground. - All right.
- 不要老盯着地上看。 - 就这样。
- Look only lnto my eyes. - Yes, all right.
我能帮你吗? 抓住我的手。
Can I help you? Here, take my h and.
- 开心吗? - 非常开心。
- Are you happy? - Very happy.
我试着去想你的样子, Rolf。。。
I try to picture you, Rolf...
我看见:
and this is what I see:
一个健壮聪明的男孩。。。
a young boy who is strong and bright...
对生活充满好奇。。。
a boy filled with curioslty about llfe...
勇于从失败中吸取教训。
a boy who lsn't afraid to learn from his mistakes.
你好,结婚的女人。
Hello, married woman.
你好。单身的男人。
Hello. bachelor man. .
恭喜。
Congratulations.
进屋吧。
Well. come in. .
日本人正在面对越来越强大的挑战。。。
The Japanese army is facing a growing challenge...
这种挑战不是来自中国的正面战场。。。
not from China 's unified front...
而是来自在毛泽东领导下的。。。
but from the powerful Chinese Communist Army.
强大的共产党军队。
Under the control of Mao Tse-tung--
有谣言说:共产党已经控制了。。。
The rumor is that the Communists have taken over...
整个中国北方。
the whole of North and Central China.
谣言? 这是事实。
Rumor? It's a fact.
从Ngawang那里 我能得到所有关于中国战场的最新消息。
Ngawang keeps me up-to-date on all China's war news.
Kungo Tsarong一家近来怎么样?
So, how are things at Kungo Tsarong's?
坦白的说我也不知道。 5个月前我就搬出去了。
Frankly, I wouldn't know. I moved out five months ago.
真的? 我们有那么长时间没有见面了?
Really? Has it been this long since we have seen you?
- 当然了。 - 最近忙吗?
- Apparently it h as. - And have you been busy?
自从他们雇我 勘测整个拉萨城以后。。。
This is why I'm extremely busy...
我就非常忙。
since I've been hired to survey the entire clty of Lhasa.
你们住得太远了, 甚至不在我的地图的范围内。
Unfortunately, your place is too far out for me to include it on my map.
我们喜欢安静。
We like our privacy.
显然是这样的。
Yes, apparently so.
关于女人呢? 你遇到喜欢的了吗?
What about women? Have you met anyone you like?
女人,
Women.
由于经历与一个奥地利女人的悲惨婚姻;
Since I failed miserably with an Austrlan wife...
与一个似乎被误导了的西藏女人的异国感情失败
an exotic failure with a Tibetan wife seems misguided.
我的答案是:没有,我没有遇到过。 你呢?
But to answer your question, no, I haven't. You?
你应该祝福我们,
A friend's good fortune is a blessing.
我很难过你憎恨我们。
I'm sorry you resent ours.
你一定非常孤独、悲伤。
You must be very lonely and sad.
战争结束了!
The war is over!
共产党赢了?
Have the Communists won?
你们的战争, 战争。 德国人投降了。
Your war, my friend. Germany has surrendered.
- 你去哪? - 回家,奥地利。
- Where are you going? - Back home. Austria.
Harrer先生, 信。
Mr. Harrer, letter.
我们会想念你的 。
We miss you .
我也会想念你们。
I miss you.
"亲爱的Helnrich Harrer先生:
"Dear Mr. Helnrich Harrer:
你不是我的爸爸。
You are not my father.
请不要再给我写信了。
Please stop writing me letters.
Rolf lmmendorf。"
Rolf lmmendorf."
尊敬的Harry Harrer先生?
Honorable Harry Harrer?
- 什么事? - 有你的信。
- Yes? - A letter for you.
尊敬的Heinrich Harrer先生 不想再要任何信件。
The Honorable Heinrich Harrer doesn't want any more letters.
是达赖喇嘛的妈妈写给你的。
It is from the Great Mother of His Holiness, the Dalai Lama.
谢谢你能来,  Harrer 先生。
Thank you for comlng, Mr. Harrer.
感谢您的邀请, Great mother。
Thank you for inviting me, Great Mother.
你知道关于我儿子的一些规矩吗?
Do you know the rules of protocol concerning my son?
不太清楚-- 我只知道见到他时要鞠躬,伏地跪拜。
Not exact-- I know one bows and performs prostrations.
当达赖喇嘛(His Holiness：尊称) 在场的时候
When you are in the presence of His Holiness...
你必须一直弯腰站着。。。
you must always be standing...
双手合十。
bent in obeisance, hands folded in supplication.
如果坐着, 必须比他坐得底。
If seated, you must always be seated lower than he.
永远不要看他的眼睛。 不要先于他说话。
Never look him in the eye. Never speak before he does.
把他称作 "Your Holiness"(宗教领袖的尊称)。
Always refer to him as "Your Holiness."
不要背朝他。 永远不要去碰他。 。
Never turn your back to him. And never. never touch him. .
他是 Avalokiteshvara菩萨 (一种极富同情心的菩萨)。。。
He is the reincarnation of Avalokiteshvara...
的转世。
the Bodhisattva of Compassion.
在他加冕之后, 他将被称作。。。
After his recognition, he was renamed...
Jetsun Jamphel Ngawang Lobsang Yeshi Tenzin Gyatso。。。
Jetsun Jamphel Ngawang Lobsang Yeshi Tenzin Gyatso...
神圣, 无上, 雄辩, 怜世。。。
Holy Lord, Gentle Glory, Eloquent, Compassionate...
的信仰守护神及大智者。
Learned Defender of the Faith , Ocean of Wisdom.
达赖喇嘛很想见你,
His Holiness, the Dalai Lama, would like to meet you.
但是他的导师不允许你们私下见面。。。
As his advisors have not permitted a private audlence with you...
所以他让我带你去参加我们母子每月一次的探望。
His Holiness has asked me to bring you along to my monthly audience.
我很荣幸能前往。
I'd be honored and moved.
黄头发。
Yellow head.
你的胳膊上也有毛吗? 腿上呢?
You have hair on your arms too? And legs?
- 你呢? - Harrer先生。
- How about you? - Mr. Harrer.
见到你真荣幸, Your Holiness。
It's an honor to meet you, Your Holiness.
你喜欢看电影吗?
Do you like movies?
你知道我已经有八年没看电影了。
You know, I haven't seen a movie in about eight years.
-但是当我回想起来的时候,我还是非常喜欢看电影的。 - 我也是。
- But as I recall, yes, very much. - So do l.
- 太好了。 - 我有一个放映机,还有一些电影。
- I'm glad to hear that. - I have a movie projector. And films.
我想让你帮我在这里建个电影院。
I want to build a movie house. Here. at the Potala. .
- 要有座位,设施齐全。 - 有座位,可以呀。
- With seats and everything. - Seats would be advisable.
你会建吗?
Can you build it?
-什么? - 你能够帮我建一个电影院吗?
- Excuse me? - Can you build a movie house for me?
我的导师不会不同意, 你也会得到大笔报酬。
My advisors cannot disapprove, and you wIll be well paid.
那你就必须每天到这里来建电影院, 每一天。
And you will have to come here every day to build it, every single day.
你在这里的时候就可以来看我。 我们可以讨论很多话题。
When you are here, you'll visit me. We can have conversations on many toplcs.
我想了解你们的世界。
I would like to learn about the world you come from.
举个例子, 巴黎在哪,法国在哪? 什么是燃烧弹?
For example, where is Paris, France? And what's a Molotov cocktall?
谁是开膛手杰克?Jack the Ripper (1888发生在伦敦的连环杀人案件,至今未侦破)
And who i s Jack the Ripper?
你可以告诉我很多事情。
You can tell me many things.
我很荣幸能为您效劳。
I'm proud to be of servlce, Your Holiness.
出什么事了?
What is the problem?
蠕虫。
Worms.
请不要再伤害蠕虫了。
Please, no more hurtlng worms.
- 蠕虫?
- Please. - Worms?
在你的前生,这无罪的蠕虫可能是你的妈妈。
In a past life, thls innocent worm could have been your mother.
不要再伤害他们了。
Please, no more h urting.
这不可能。  请不要再伤害了。
It's impossible. Please, no more.
但是你应该知道, 藏民相信。。。
But you see, Tibetans believe...
所有的动物都可能是你前世的妈妈。
all living creatures were their mothers in a past life.
因此我们必须尊重并报答他们。。
So we must show them respect and repay their kindness.
再也不要伤害任何动物了。
And never, never harm anything that lives.
你无法让那些虔诚的信徒不遵守那些珍贵的教义。
You can't ask a devout people to disregard a precious teaching.
是的, 但是。。。
Yes, but Your Holin ess...
我真的尊重, 但我们不可能--
with true respect, we can't possibly--
但是我们不可能保护所有的蠕虫。。。
I'm sorry, but we can't possibly rescue all the worms...
否则的话这辈子电影院也建不成。
not if you want a theater finished in this lifetime.
你很聪明,你会有办法的。
You have a clever mind. Think of a solution.
现在顺便告诉我： 电梯是什么东西？
And in the meantime, you can explaln to me what is an elevator.
南极洲。 在下面。
Antarctica. That's down below.
这里。
Here.
棒极了。
Fantastic.
英格兰。
Englan d.
别向我求助。
Don't look at me for h elp.
这儿?
Here?
加速。
Shift.
嘿，我认识他。 你好，Honk！
Oh, I know him. Honk. Hello!
转弯!
Turn !
刹车!
Brake!
大臣(a minister)的藏袍 比你原来的褐色藏袍精致多了,是吗?
The robe of a minister is so much finer than your old brown robe, i sn't it?
请。
Please.
大家都请坐下。
Everyone, please.
提升的那么快。你一定是非常精干了。
You must be very clever to get such a good promotion.
我从没想过要一辈子当秘书。
I did not intend to be a secretary forever.
显而易见。
Apparently so.
祝贺你。
Well , congratulations.
不祥的征兆!
Evil omen !
北京中央消息。。。
From his headquarters in Peking...
毛泽东主席是当之无愧的。。。
the Chairman, Mao Tse-tung, was triumphantly proclaimed leader...
新中国的领导者。
of the new People 's Republic of China.
毛主席承诺共产主义政权的第一个任务就是。。。
Chairman Mao vowed that the first task of the Communist regime...
重新统一中国大陆。
is to reunite the Chinese motherland.
他宣布遥远的西藏。。。
He declared that the remote kingdom of Tibet...
也是中国领土不可分割的一部分。。。
Is an lntegral part of the Chinese territory...
因此必须加入新的共和国。
and must join the great new republic.
“。。。必须加入新的共和国。”
"...and must join the great n ew republic."
中华人民共和国必须知道：
People's Republic of China is advised...
西藏政府不承认任何外国政权对其具有管辖权
the government of Tibet recognizes no foreign sovereign.
我们是一个独立的国家。
We are an independent nation.
所有的中国官员都将被驱逐出西藏。
All the Chinese officials will be expelled from the borders of Tibet.
祝你们回国愉快。
We wish you a happy return to your h omeland.
一路顺风。
Have a safe and pleasant journey back to China.
May you have a safe and pleasant journey back to China.
回国愉快。
We wish you a happy return to your homeland.
祝你开心，事业兴旺发达。
May you have happiness and prosperity.
让我看看。
Let me see.
你的生命线和长，不像这里的其他人。。
You have a very long lifeline, unlike others here.
当我们在朝向太阳时， 就是白天，对不对？
When we are faclng the light, it's day, yes?
当我们在阴面的时候, 就是晚上。
When we are in shadow, it's night.
所以当拉萨日出的时候。。。
So if the sun is just rising in Lhasa...
这就意味着。。。
that means it is just setting...
纽约大概是日落的时候。
in New York City, perhaps.
这就是世界各地的时间各不相同的原因。
That's why it can't be the same time in every place.
- 明白了? - 嗯!
- Does that answer your question? - Yes!
再多告诉我一些。
Tell me more.
你现在还想知道什么?
What else do you want to know?
再过一会你将进入 奇妙的大众传媒的世界。
In a few moments, you wIll be entering the world of mass media.
我能听见来自世界各地的新闻?
I can hear news from all over the planet?
我不知道汤加群岛上是否也有电台,
I don't know if they have live broadcasts from the Tonga lslands...
但是一般来说, 是的。
but generally speaking, yeah.
你听来自你祖国的新闻吗?
Do you listen to news from your country?
奥地利? 不,不常听。
From Austri a? No, not really.
照一下, Ku-Dun。
Give me some light, Ku-Dun.
- 为什么?那是你的家。 - 不再是了。
- Why? It's your home. - Not anymore It isn't.
你在那里有朋友和家庭吗?
But don't you have friends and family there?
有几个朋友, 没有家。
A few friends, no family.
照着不要动, Your Holiness。
Keep the light steady, Your Holiness.
为什么? 家人都死了?
Why? ls everyone dead?
你怎么有那么多问题?
Do you know there's another sentence construction aside from the question?
我结过婚,但是离婚了。
I was married, but I'm divorced.
你做了什么?
What did you do?
我不想要孩子, 于是跑去爬山。
I didn't want a child, so I ran away to climb a mountain.
你有孩子?
You h ave a child?
但从来没见过。
Although I've never seen hlm.
好了,现在让我演示一下, 它是怎么工作的。
All right. Let me show you how this thing works.
-就这样别乱动。 -好的, Harrer 先生。
- Glve it all you've got. - Yes, Mr. Harrer.
圣诞快乐。
Happy Christmas.
谢谢。
Thank you.
-这是什么特别的日子? - 圣诞节。
- What is this special occasion? - This is Chrlstmas.
这是给你的,朋友。 拿着。
And this is for you, my friend. Go on.
我在 Barkhor 一家店里找到它的。
"I found it in a shop in the Barkhor.
经过一段漫长的旅行之后它回家了。
It has traveled a long way and finally come back home.
感谢你的友谊 Heinrich。
Thank you for your friendshlp. Heinrich. "
不可思议。
It is incredible.
谢谢你救了我的命。
Thank you for saving my life.
。。。必须从宗教压迫中解放。
...must be liberated from religlous oppressors.
西藏人民。。。
Tibetans must be reunited...
-必须和新中国大家庭的兄弟姐妹。。。 -关掉它。
- with their brothers and sisters... - Turn that off.
- 团结起来。 - 对不起。
- of the great family of new China. - I'm very sorry.
外国人控制了腐败的西藏政府。
Foreigners control Tibet's corrupt government.
西藏的同志们必须从帝国主义的压迫中解放出来。
Our Tibetan comrades must be liberated from foreign imperialists.
西藏的百万农奴必须解放。
Tibet 's million serfs must be freed.
西藏有多少外国人?
How many foreigners are there in Tibet?
你和Heinrich。
You, Heinrich.
西藏将会解放。
Tibet will be liberated.
他要见你, Harrer先生。
He asked for you, Mr. Harrer.
他们毁灭了我出生的城市——Takster in Amdo。
They were destroying the village I was born in, Takster in Amdo.
真恐怖。
It was terrible.
这只是梦。 你做了个恶梦而已。
It was just a dream. You had a bad dream. That's all.
但那是如此真实。 它们从哪来?
But it was so real. Where did it come from?
我无法想象如此恐怖的事情。
My mind could never imagine such terrible things.
我睡不着。 害怕恶梦会再回来
I can't sleep. I'm afraid the dream will come back.
失眠。
A couple of insomniacs.
给我讲个故事。
Tell me a story.
讲一个关于爬山的故事
Tell me a story about cllmbing mountains.
这是催眠的好方法。 那些故事连我都烦。
That's one way to fall asleep. Those stories bore even me.
那么告诉我你爱什么。
Then tell me what you love about it.
是什么呢--
What--
一定是简单。 那是我的最爱。
The absolute simplicity. That's what I love.
当你爬山的时候, 你特别清醒。。。
When you're climbing, your mind is clear...
没有杂念。
freed of all confusions.
你注意力集中。
You have focus.
忽然光线变得刺眼。。。
And suddenly the light becomes sharper...
声音变得震耳。。。
sounds are rlcher...
然后你感觉到。。。
and you are filled with...
生命的强大。
the deep, powerful presence of life.
在另外一个时刻, 我也曾经有过一次那样的感觉
I've only felt that way one other time.
什么时候?
When?
见到你的时候, Ku-Dun。
In your presence, Ku-Dun.
中国人已经占领了北疆的大部分地区。
The Chinese have already secured much of the northern border regions.
他们掠夺村庄, 摧毁寺庙。。。
They have ransacked a village, destroyed the monasteries...
焚烧经文,亵渎神灵。
burnt scriptures and defaced holy relics.
甚至杀死了一些喇嘛……
We've been told they've even killed some monks--
-哪个村庄? - Takster in Amdo。
- Which vill age? - Takster in Amdo.
达赖喇嘛在那里出生。
It's where His Holiness was born.
Go ahead。
Go ahead.
当你出任前任达赖喇嘛的国防大臣时。。。
When you were defense minister to the previous Dalai Lama...
你想组建军队。
then you wanted to reorganlze the army.
你现在可以做吗?
Can you do it now?
人民解放军有百万之众。
The People's Liberation Army is one million troops strong.
我们只有8000个人50门炮。。。
We have 8,000 men with 50 pieces of artillery...
和几百门迫击炮以及一些机枪。
and a few hundred mortars and machine guns.
这毫无希望。
The task is hopeless.
那你拒绝这个任务了，是吗?
Then you refuse the appointment, do you?
不是。 我很荣幸的接受。
No. I accept it with honor.
你们两位先生应该了解武器。
You two gentlemen know about wars.
有什么武器可以推荐?
What type of weapon do you recommend?
中国军队好像正在向我们的北疆挺进。
It seems the Chinese troops are advancing toward our northern borders.
达赖喇嘛去哪了?
Where's His Holiness?
大不列颠加冕的荣耀。
The glory of a British coronation.
这是世界上最隆重的事情。
Nowhere in the world is there anything half so wonderful.
你一生中只能见证一次或两次这样的时刻。。。
Only once or twice in the life of each one of us comes such a day as this...
当我们意识到 我们正在目睹创造历史。。。
when we know that we are watchlng history in the making...
当我们意识到我们的后代将会想起今天——。。。
when we know that generations to come will look back on this day...
1937年5月12日, 这一天将注定成为历史。。。
for May 12, 1937, wIll be one of the dates in hlstory...
或许一千年里孩子们都要学习这段历史。
that schoolchildren will learn about maybe a thousand years from now.
每一刻都令人兴奋发抖……
Every moment the thrill of excitement--
你觉得会有人在银幕上看见西藏。。。
Do you thlnk someday people will look at Tibet on the movie screen...
并想知道那里发生了什么?
and wonder what happened to us?
加冕的四轮大马车向前移动了。
The coronation coach moves forward.
我不知道。
I don't know.
你不是什么都知道吗?
Don't you have all the answers?
我不是。
I don't.
在藏民传统的聚会的场地上。。。
On the same field where Tibetans traditionally gathered for picnics...
正在建造一条飞机跑道。。。
ground was cleared to build an alrstrip...
一边载着中国将军的飞机可以着落。
so that the plane carrying three Chinese generals could land.
附近,西藏的军队正在进行机动性训练。
Nearby, the Tibetan army practiced its maneuvers.
一些士兵穿着古老的盔甲。
Some of the soldiers wear ancient mesh armour.
他们把老式的步枪和长矛当作大炮。
They bring old muskets and spears as artillery.
这是一幅—— 一个热爱和平的民族正在徒劳的建立一支军队的景象。
The spectacle of a peace-lovlng nation, vainly attempting to create a mllitary.
我的朋友的脸上对战争的恐惧。。。
The fears of war on my friends ' faces...
深深地震撼了每个人的神经。
strike a deeply burled personal chord.
我的祖国（德国）的侵略性。。。
Echoes of the aggressions of my own country...
以及征服弱小民族欲望。。。
the will to overpower weaker peoples...
让我感到羞辱。
bring shame to me.
很久以来我想到这些就感到战栗。。。
I shudder to recall how once long ago I embraced the same beliefs...
事实上。。。
how at one time I was, in fact...
这些狭隘的中国人也在做同样的事情。
no different from these intolerant Chinese.
藏民认为敌人是最好的老师。。。
The Tibetans say an enemy is the greatest teacher...
因为只有敌人可以磨练你的容忍, 让你富有同情心。
because only an enemy can help develop patience and compassion.
他们坚信宗教的力量。。。
They believe with rock-llke faith that the power of their religion...
将保护他们免遭遭难。
will protect them against these Chinese.
为了迎接中国将军的来访。。。
In preparation for the generals ' visit...
整个拉萨都在进行神圣的宗教礼仪。
sacred ceremonies are performed throughout Lhasa.
人们非常细心的用黄油雕刻神像。
Sculptures of deities have been carved with great care in butter.
当太阳将其熔化时,她提醒人们什么也不存在。
As the sun melts them, they become a reminder that nothlng lasts.
冉冉升起的政治新星, 大臣 Ngawang Jigme。。。
The rising star of the cabinet, Minister Ngawang Jigme...
自做主张同意中国将军。。。
made an offering of his own to greet the Chinese generals...
访问西藏。
and lead them through Lhasa.
中国不应该享受升起国旗的荣耀。
Raising their flag is an honor the Chinese don't deserve.
当你不是足够强大的时候, 你就应该拥抱你的敌人。
When you are not strong enough to fight, you should embrace your enemy.
当他两手抱你的时候, 他就没法用枪指着你了。
With both arms around you, he cannot point a gun at you.
在政治上没有什么荣耀可谈。
Nothing in politics is a matter of honor, my friend.
即使在天堂历史也会重复。
History repeats itself, even in paradise.
将军,我们将去和达赖喇嘛会面--
General, we shall have our audience with His--
将军, 僧侣们制作这个沙坛已经很多天了。
General, the monks have been making this mandala of sand for many days.
它象征启蒙和和平。
It is a symbol of enlightenment and peace.
将军 !
General !
我们不会比他坐得低。
We do not sit lower than he does.
但是,将军这是我们习惯。
But, General, It is our custom.
我可以坐在下面。
I can sit down there.
Your Holiness, 这是张经武将军。。。
Your Holiness, this is General Chang Jing Wu...
Than Gua将军, Than Gua San将军。
General Than Gua, General Than Gua San.
他们想和你会谈。
They wish to have an audience with you.
祝你们快乐健康。
May you have happiness and prosperity.
如果西藏接受中国的政治管辖, 他们保证。。。
They are promising regional autonomy and religious freedom...
西藏的宗教自治和信仰自有。
if Tibet accepts that China be its political master.
在我成年以前,  the regent(摄政王)才是西藏的政治领袖 。
Until I attain my majority, the regent ls the political leader of Tibet.
你们应该和他去谈这些。。。
You should have requested an audlence with him...
。。。国家大事。
to discuss these important matters of the world.
这方面我的经验有限,
My experience of such things is limited.
我只是一个简单的佛教僧侣。
I am a simple Buddhist monk.
我所知道的只有经文和佛所说的。
All I know is the scripture and the words of Lord Buddha.
他说：“所有的人都会在 危险和死亡面前颤抖，
He sald, "All beings tremble before danger and death.
生命是最珍贵的，
Life is dear to all.
如果人们意识到这一点他就不会杀生。”
When a man considers this, he does not kill or cause to kill."
你们必须知道。
You must understand.
这些话深植于每个藏民的心中，
These words are ingrained in the heart of every Tibetan.
这就是为什么我们 热爱和平、拒绝暴力。
It ls why we are a peaceful people who reject violence on principle.
希望你们能把这一点看作我们最强大的力量。。。
I pray you will see this is our greatest strength...
而不是弱点。
not our weakness.
感谢你的来访。
I thank you for your vislt.
宗教是毒药。
Rellgion is poison.
在Den-Go附近中国向西藏边境发起进攻。
The Chinese have attacked the Tlbetan frontier near Den-Go.
今天拂晓在张经武将军的指挥下。。。
"Today at the dawn, 84,000 troops of the 1st and 2nd Field Armles...
第一、二野战军84，000人。。。
under the overall command of General Chang Jing Wu...
在Den－Go附近向西藏发起攻击。
attacked the Tibetan frontier near Den-Go.
西藏方面认为中国 对Chamdo的进攻也迫在眉睫。
The Tibetan army believes an attack on Chamdo is imminent.
Ngawang Jigme,我们新的代总理。。。
Ngawang Jigme, our newly appointed governor...
正在将部队派往中国部队所在地区。。。
is preparing to send troops toward the Chinese column...
以阻止他们前进。
In order to stop their progresslon. "
如你所知, Chamdo是西藏的大门。
As you know, Chamdo is the gateway to Tibet.
如果 Chamdo 失守，西藏就完了。
If Chamdo falls. . the whole of Tibet will fall.
如果我连这一点都不知道 我就不会是代总理了。
If I did not know that, I would not have been appointed governor.
你应该知道我将战斗到最后一个人。
You do realize our troops are committed to fighting the Chinese to the last man.
宁愿战死也不投降。
They would rather die than surrender.
毫无疑问，只要我在Chamdo 就不会有投降的。
Rest assured. there will be no surrender . as long as I am in Chamdo.
拉萨电台。
Radio Lh asa.
现在
Now.
我们请求投降。
We request permission to surrender.
- 但是这里不会有人投降-- - 我说了, “拉萨电台”
- But there will be no surrender-- - I said, "Radio Lh asa."
现在我们请求投降。
Permission to surrender now.
我们11天内输掉了这场战争, Heinrich。
We lost the war in 11 days, Heinrich.
投降是对我们最后的宣判。
This surrender is our death sentence.
我担心我们的朋友 Ngawang Jigme已经出卖了我们。
And I'm afraid our friend Ngawang Jigme has issued it.
他放弃了Chamdo并且炸毁了临时军火库。
He abandoned Chamdo and then destroyed the ammunition dumps.
没有武器弹药。。。
Without weapons and ammunition...
那些想血拼到底的士兵也无法战斗。
there was no hope for the troops who wanted to fight.
本来我们的游击队可以在山上据守几个月。。。
Our guerrillas could have held the mountain passes for months...
甚至几年。
even years.
这样我们就有时间向其他国家求助。
It would have bought us time to make appeals for help to other nations.
现在一点希望都没有了。
Now it's lost.
他们毁掉了西藏的大门。
They broke down the gates.
你好，老朋友。
Hello, my friend.
对于西藏。。。
We did what was the best for our country...
我们已经做了最好的选择。
for Tibet.
在来拉萨的路上， 我看见藏民穿着这样的夹克。
On the way to Lhasa, I would see Tibetans wearing these jackets.
“中国士兵非常好。
"Chinese soldiers. Very nice.
给粮食、衣服、钱，非常好。”
Glve food, clothes, money. Very nice."
对我来说这有点奇怪—— 像夹克这样平淡无奇的东西。。。
It's strange to me that something so harmless as a jacket...
居然暗示了一个巨大的谎言。
could symbolize such a great lie.
经过了这些年，你仍然不明白藏民的习俗。
After all these years, you still do not understand Tibetan ways.
归还别人礼物，是不可宽恕的。。
To return a gift is unforgivable.
一个背叛了民族的人没有权力来鼓吹所谓的规则。
A man who betrays his culture should not preach about its customs.
曾经有一刻，我诅咒你早死。。。
There was a time I would have wished you dead...
但是你的羞辱将变成你的痛苦，
but your shame will be your torture.
而痛苦将成为你生命的全部，
And your torture will be your life.
我希望它越长越好。
I wish it to be long.
我们祈求授予达赖喇嘛权力。。。
We pray that His Holiness, the Dalai Lama...
去团结他的人民。
will be granted the power to unify his people.
我们谨要求西藏政府尊重我们的愿望。。。
We humbly ask the Tibetan government to honor our request...
让达赖喇嘛登基。
and let the Dalai Lama attain his political majority.
你让大家都急死了。
You have the entire palace in a panlc.
我只是想躲起来一天而已。
I'm hiding from the world for a day.
在玻璃房里躲着挺难的，不是吗？
Kind of difficult in a glasshouse, no?
月光曲。。。
It's The Moonlight...
德彪西的。
by Debussy.
关于这首曲子你还知道些什么？
What else do you know about this song?
这匹、这匹还有这匹。
Him, him and him.
我想你已经收到了登基典礼的邀请。
I hope you've received your invitation to the enthronement ceremony.
是的，谢谢。
Yes. Thank you.
- 在下个星期。 - 谢谢你。
- It's next week. - Th ank you.
我看起来像个老学究吗?
Do I look like an egghead?
不，眼镜很配你。
No, they suit you.
西藏有一种说法。。。
We have a saying in Tibet...
“如果是一个可以解决的问题，那就没必要担心它；
"If the problem can be solved, there is no use worrying about it.
如果是不能解决的问题，担心也没用。
If it can't be solved. . worrying will do no good."
所以别担心。
So stop worrying.
你必须离开西藏，在这里有生命危险。
You have to leave Tibet. Your life's at great risk.
请原谅我的冒失， 我已经安排好让你安全离开。
Forgive my presumption, but I made arrangements to get you out safely.
我们必须在典礼前离开， 中国人不会接受的。
We should leave after the enthronement. The Chinese would never expect it--
如果我逃跑了我怎么帮助这里的人们？ 那我成了什么样的领袖？
How can I help people if I run away from them? What kind of leader would I be?
我必须留在这里。
I have to stay here.
帮助别人就是解放自己。
Serving others is my path to liberation .
-那我也不离开。 - 为什么不?
- Then I don't go either. - Why not?
因为你是我的自由之路。
Because you are my path to liberation.
佛主说：拯救不是源之佛的眼睛，
The Buddha sald. "Salvation . does not come from the slght of me.
而是需要你去努力实践，
It demands strenuous effort and practice.
勤奋工作并探求自我拯救。
So work hard and seek your own salvation diligently."
我不是你的儿子。。。
I am not your son...
也从不把你当父亲看。
and I never thought of you as my father.
这个对于我来说，你是太不正式的了。
You were much too informal with me for that.
你想他吗?
Do you ever think about him?
想什么?
And wh at do you think about?
这真的不是有意识地去想。
It's not the conscious thought really.
他总是在那里。
It's just always there.
我穿越西藏时，他就在身边；
When I crossed Tibet, he was with me.
我来到拉萨，他在我身边；
When I came to Lhasa. . he was with me.
我坐在你旁边时， 他。。。
When I sit beside you, he's...
也在我身边。
there with me.
我甚至不能想象没有他， 这个世界会变成什么样。
I can't even imagine how I pictured the world without him in it.
所以你应该回家，去做他的父亲。
Then you should go home and be his father.
我知道。
I know.
你在这里的任务已经完成了。
You have finished your job with me.
但是你必须留下来参加即位典礼。
But you have to stay for my enthronement.
你可以看见华丽、荣耀的我。
I want you to see me in all my pomp and glory.
非常荣幸。
It'd be a pleasure, my friend.
西藏政府。。。
From the government of Tibet...
十四世达赖喇嘛。。。
to Your Holin ess, the fourteenth Dalai Lama...
作为西藏精神和万物的领袖。。。
we ask you to rule your people...
我们请求您普渡众生。
as the spiritual and temporal leader of Tibet.
据你们的祈祷和愿望 我谨接受。
By your prayers and wishes, I humbly accept.
奶茶，我从来都不喜欢。
Butter tea. It was never my cup of tea.
-一杯足够了。 - 是的，但我们必须入乡随俗。
- One was enough. - Yes, we must follow the custom.
一杯热茶送亲人。
A fresh cup of tea is poured for the loved one departing.
不要动它， 等他回来再喝。
It sits untouched, walting for hls return.
愿所有的旅行者快乐相伴，
May all travelers find happiness wherever they go.
心想事成，
Without any effort may they accomplish whatever they set out to do.
平安到达，
And having safely returned to the shore...
家人重聚。。
may they be joyfully reunited with their relatives.
Harrer先生
Mr. Harrer...
His Holiness达赖喇嘛给你的。
from His Holiness.
- 你好 Horst。 -你好 Heinrich。
- Hello, Horst. - Hello, Heinrich.
Rolf,出来见见他。
Rolf, come out to meet him.
不，我不想。。
No, I don't want to.
我可以进去吗？
May l ?
Rolf，抓紧时间。
Rolf, take your time.
干得好，儿子。
Well done, son.
干得好。
Well done.